<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://itepifanio.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://itepifanio.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2023-10-11T19:32:28+00:00</updated><id>https://itepifanio.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Bloguito</title><subtitle>Web dev &amp; more.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Enhancing Python Project Productivity: The Advantages of Mamba for Environment Management</title><link href="https://itepifanio.github.io/2023/07/11/mamba-advantages.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Enhancing Python Project Productivity: The Advantages of Mamba for Environment Management" /><published>2023-07-11T16:03:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-11T16:03:00+00:00</updated><id>https://itepifanio.github.io/2023/07/11/mamba-advantages</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://itepifanio.github.io/2023/07/11/mamba-advantages.html">&lt;p&gt;The multitude of
&lt;a href=&quot;https://packaging.python.org/en/latest/glossary/#term-Virtual-Environment&quot;&gt;Python environments&lt;/a&gt; 
management choices can leave even senior Python developers unsure of the best tool usage.
This article describes how Palaimon reduced costs while increase productivity by choosing to use mamba/micromamba 
for environment management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tools like pip, conda, venv, &lt;a href=&quot;https://python-poetry.org/&quot;&gt;poetry&lt;/a&gt;, and others, have served us well over time. 
But like most things in the dynamic world of programming, we continuously evolve to meet new challenges and improve 
existing systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/snake-and-computer.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image create with help from stable diffusion model Deliberate V2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Palaimon develops complex data projects which requires the usage of multiple dependencies. &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pip&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;virtualenv&lt;/code&gt; are the “go to” 
way to manage environment and handle dependencies in Python but Conda packages are a better solution for Machine Learning projects. 
Conda includes cross-language dependencies and isolated environment setup with more stable packages and GPU support (which is key for us).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conda’s impressive capability comes with performance issues which leads to workarounds like 
&lt;a href=&quot;(https://ealizadeh.com/blog/guide-to-python-env-pkg-dependency-using-conda-poetry#the-proposed-setup)&quot;&gt;combining conda with other tools&lt;/a&gt;
to optimize the setup. In the past we tried to combine Conda and &lt;a href=&quot;https://python-poetry.org/&quot;&gt;poetry&lt;/a&gt; but these kind of workarounds can lead 
to its own complexities and are not ideal for all scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s where mamba comes into play. If you’re not familiar, mamba is a reimplementation of the conda package manager, written in C++. 
This transition to a compiled language means that mamba provides a 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://pythonspeed.com/articles/faster-conda-install/&quot;&gt;significant performance boost&lt;/a&gt;, particularly when resolving 
dependencies, which can take a lot of time in larger projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Mamba offers all the advantages of conda with significantly speed improvement. Faster environment solving means less  waiting and more time for coding&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mamba allowed our team to config a better, faster and cheaper CI (Continuos Integration), improving the team productivity. 
Its compatibility with conda environment and packages made the transition from conda to mamba very easy since all commands 
the team used are kept the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Palaimon GmbH, we understand the importance of effective Python environment management, and we’ve adopted 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://mamba.readthedocs.io/en/latest/user_guide/micromamba.html&quot;&gt;micromamba&lt;/a&gt;, a tiny version of mamba. This tooling 
addresses many of the challenges we’re faced with when managing complex Python environments while reducing our docker images costs, 
making the CI maintenance cheaper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Managing Python environments is a vital aspect of Python development, and choosing the right tool can significantly impact 
your team productivity, the quality of your work and CI costs. At Palaimon GmbH we are excited about the possibilities 
mamba/micromamba offers and we highly recommend giving it a try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;
Text created with the help of AI
&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The multitude of Python environments management choices can leave even senior Python developers unsure of the best tool usage. This article describes how Palaimon reduced costs while increase productivity by choosing to use mamba/micromamba for environment management.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">PyCon US 2023</title><link href="https://itepifanio.github.io/2023/05/07/pycon-2023.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PyCon US 2023" /><published>2023-05-07T13:39:20+00:00</published><updated>2023-05-07T13:39:20+00:00</updated><id>https://itepifanio.github.io/2023/05/07/pycon-2023</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://itepifanio.github.io/2023/05/07/pycon-2023.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;pycon-us-2023&quot;&gt;PyCon US 2023&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PyCon US is the largest annual convention for the Python programming language. 
The event took place from April 19 to April 27 in &lt;a href=&quot;https://goo.gl/maps/2V9ofSHdHciUxRcg7&quot;&gt;Salt Lake City, Utah&lt;/a&gt;.
I was thrilled to contribute with a tutorial, attend insightful talks, and checked 
the PyCon news announcements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/pycon-2023/conference_passport.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;News, such as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.pypi.org/posts/2023-04-23-introducing-pypi-organizations/&quot;&gt;PyPI organizations feature&lt;/a&gt;, 
and retrospectives like the one conducted by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guido_van_Rossum&quot;&gt;Guido Van Rossum&lt;/a&gt; 
were key part of the conference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;talks&quot;&gt;Talks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PyCon has two tracks of talks, one in English and another in Spanish called “Las Charlas”.
All of them will be available on YouTube in near future. You can find them &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/c/pyconus&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most fun talk I attended was on how to &lt;a href=&quot;https://us.pycon.org/2023/schedule/presentation/142/&quot;&gt;Create interactive games using MicroPython and electronics&lt;/a&gt;. 
It introduced me to the new world of MicroPython and how to program games using a board 
called &lt;a href=&quot;https://makecode.microbit.org/&quot;&gt;micro:bit&lt;/a&gt;. The micro:bit board was design for children, 
it doesn’t have pins or connectors that can harm them and it already comes with a lot of pre-programmed 
features. Check out the 30-second “Chase the dot” video (sound on) and see how much fun is to program these small games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/NVJH6F-3XuU&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tutorials&quot;&gt;Tutorials&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was gratifying to contribute to the event by tutoring advanced topics in Jupyter Notebooks. 
The tutorial &lt;a href=&quot;https://us.pycon.org/2023/schedule/presentation/2/&quot;&gt;Going beyond with Jupyter Notebooks: Write your first package using literate programming&lt;/a&gt; 
was well-attended and presented the usage of nbdev for writing Python packages using Jupyter notebooks. 
The tutorial also introduced advanced topics like testing, code quality tools, and how to build UIs for Jupyter notebooks.
All the tooling presented is used in Palaimon’s workflow to build and document its products.
The presentation &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/itepifanio/going-beyond-with-jupyter-notebooks/blob/main/presentation/presentation.pdf&quot;&gt;is available here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/pycon-2023/tutorial_room.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;announcements&quot;&gt;Announcements&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest announcement was the introduction of organization accounts for the Python Packaging Index (PyPI), which was one of the 
most requested features of the platform. PyPI will now be easier to use with large teams that need to 
manage sub-teams and multiple packages. This feature will be free for community projects and available at 
a small fee for corporate projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is crucial for the financial sustainability of PyPI, as the number of downloads has been growing (57% in the last period) and 
its infrastructure is currently subsidized by AWS. The Python Software Foundation (PSF) has been working diligently on the 
financial sustainability of the organization. They announced that PyCon US now accounts for 75% of its annual income 
(previously was around 90%) and reported a pilot partnership with an educational program that may serve as an 
additional source of income for the organization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;keynotes&quot;&gt;Keynotes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The keynote “Python: The People’s Programming Language” by Carol Willing really stood out to me.
Carol delved into distributed computing and network concepts to discuss resilient community networks.
It was an intimate talk that touched on personal challenges and community accomplishments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/pycon-2023/carol_willing_keynote.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guido Van Rossum, the creator of Python, initially played a trick on us with the talk 
“Feed CPython to ChatGPT: can we use AI to make Python faster?”. He later discussed 
previous PyCon US events, shared stories, and provided insights about Python’s past and future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/pycon-2023/guido_keynote.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PyCon is a diverse and inclusive conference that embraces the community. The tutorials, 
talks, and keynotes are awesome, but the best part of the event is connecting with people, 
sharing knowledge, and discussing topics you’re passionate about. The biggest challenge of the 
conference is making the most of your time there.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">PyCon US 2023</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2022 Recap</title><link href="https://itepifanio.github.io/2023/01/01/recap-2022.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2022 Recap" /><published>2023-01-01T16:09:20+00:00</published><updated>2023-01-01T16:09:20+00:00</updated><id>https://itepifanio.github.io/2023/01/01/recap-2022</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://itepifanio.github.io/2023/01/01/recap-2022.html">&lt;p&gt;2022 was a long year. Tech market started to cool down and even some 
big techs started to layoff people, some friends got caught in the middle of this but 
were able to find a new place to work. Brazilian politics had a huge battle for democracy 
(that we fortunately win). I learn a lot of challenging things on the AI field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2021 my focus on AI study was on data annotation and labelling. In 2022 I helped to customize and extend AI products focused on computer vision and object detection. This kind of projects requires a lot of efforts in the pre and pos processing, and a lot of additional steps, like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Data_Version_Control&quot;&gt;data versioning&lt;/a&gt;, to guarantee reproducibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;events&quot;&gt;Events&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started to be engaged with the tech community by giving talks and organizing events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talked:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;At &lt;a href=&quot;https://2022.pythonnordeste.org/&quot;&gt;Python Nordeste 2022&lt;/a&gt; (biggest Python event in the northeast of Brazil) 
about my work on the open source lib &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/palaimon/ipyannotator&quot;&gt;Ipyannotator&lt;/a&gt; and how it can be 
used for terrestrial traffic annotation, using the &lt;a href=&quot;https://palaimon.io/projects.html#sec-cc&quot;&gt;CityCount project&lt;/a&gt; 
as an example.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/CgSt2CgLTyQ/&quot;&gt;V PHPRN meetup&lt;/a&gt;, returning to the in-person events. I talked about my 
experience with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://tallstack.dev/&quot;&gt;TALL stack&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organized:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/CgSt2CgLTyQ/&quot;&gt;V PHPRN meetup&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/CiVN31LrtaR/&quot;&gt;IX Meetup GrupyRN&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/CkgPmVBOG4j/&quot;&gt;Python Day 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://phprn.github.io/phpeste/&quot;&gt;PHPeste 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was my first year organizing events and managing the tech community. It is so much more work than I tought initially, 
talking with the community, designing things, updating websites and social media, scheduling the space, searching for sponsors, ordering the food, and generating certificates. I learned a lot about accessibility, there’s always room for improvement but I think we were in the right direction at the Python Day, with food for everyone (vegan, gluten-free, milk-free, sugar-free), no applauses for people with a sensibility to high sounds, and efforts to have a space that embrace all genders, races, and sexualities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;exploring&quot;&gt;Exploring&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Learned about &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Computer_graphics&quot;&gt;computer graphics&lt;/a&gt; by developing a simple C++ raytracer that 
read a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.xml&lt;/code&gt; file and output a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.ppm&lt;/code&gt; image file with a 3D scene. It was one of the most challenging projects for me because 
I have &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aphantasia&quot;&gt;aphantasia&lt;/a&gt;, not been able to draw mental images was a issue to debug camera 
projections and abstract some angles calculations.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Studied about metrics that measure the quality of projects with object orientation. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://tinylog.org/v2/&quot;&gt;Tinylog&lt;/a&gt; (Java version) quality was investigated by measuring its &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cyclomatic_complexity&quot;&gt;Cyclometic complexity&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fan-out_(software)#Software_design_and_quality_assurance&quot;&gt;fan-out&lt;/a&gt; and other simple metrics.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Published 4 posts on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.palaimon.io/&quot;&gt;Palaimon Blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Published a paper about Ipyannotator on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://joss.theoj.org/papers/10.21105/joss.04480&quot;&gt;Journal of Open Software (JOSS)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Took more responsabilities as a data engineer. I developed an &lt;a href=&quot;https://intake.readthedocs.io/en/latest/&quot;&gt;intake&lt;/a&gt; plugin 
to help the team to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Data_Version_Control&quot;&gt;versionate its data and experiments&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Learn lots of usages and pain of OpenCV by working on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.palaimon.io/posts/citycount-finalization/&quot;&gt;CityCount study&lt;/a&gt;. This project was a good test case for the data versioning intake solution and Ipyannotator lib.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tested, refactored and extended AI solutions for &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Multiple_object_tracking&quot;&gt;Multiple Object Tracking (MOT)&lt;/a&gt;. Most of the AI project don’t test its code which makes difficult to refactor and extend them, 
for our use case it was necessary to write tests before touching the code, increasing the quality of the software and the understanding of the code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">2022 was a long year. Tech market started to cool down and even some big techs started to layoff people, some friends got caught in the middle of this but were able to find a new place to work. Brazilian politics had a huge battle for democracy (that we fortunately win). I learn a lot of challenging things on the AI field.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Python Nordeste 2022 Recap</title><link href="https://itepifanio.github.io/2022/09/09/python-nordeste.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Python Nordeste 2022 Recap" /><published>2022-09-09T16:09:20+00:00</published><updated>2022-09-09T16:09:20+00:00</updated><id>https://itepifanio.github.io/2022/09/09/python-nordeste</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://itepifanio.github.io/2022/09/09/python-nordeste.html">&lt;p&gt;From August 26th to August 28th 2022 I attended the Python Nordeste,
the biggest Python event in northeast of Brazil. It was the return of in-person
conferences in the country. Focused on the communities, the event slogan was
“People &amp;gt; Technology”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;width: 60%; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; display: block;&quot; alt=&quot;Python Nordeste entry. A big and light panel with the title 'PyNE 2022' and a pacman game design&quot; src=&quot;/assets/python-nordeste-entrance.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;
Event entry. Picture by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/raphaelfontes/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Rafael Fontes&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a good mix of technical talks and community discussions the event happened in 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://goo.gl/maps/2hvCA44yKiJPBdDv9&quot;&gt;Aracaju&lt;/a&gt;, 
the city with the “most beautiful beachfront” 
(a controversial topic since most of the principal cities are coastal).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I gave a talk that showed how &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/palaimon/ipyannotator&quot;&gt;Ipyannotator&lt;/a&gt; 
can be used for traffic annotations and presented the results 
of our R&amp;amp;D project CityCount.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a quick overview of some talks I attended:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Community, diversity and inclusion: challenges and strategy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Algorithmic biases and how to combat them&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How AI can impact the population’s health?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Using Ipyannotator for traffic annotation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;community-diversity-and-inclusion-challenges-and-strategy&quot;&gt;Community, diversity and inclusion: challenges and strategy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brazil has a very diverse population that is not completely represented 
in the technological field. Multiple communities were built to create safe-spaces 
and encourage underrepresented people to move into the area. This 
talk was an open discussion about strategies and challenges to use technology 
as a tool for social transformation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Technology can be a tool for social transformation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The discussion was conducted by four members of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://brasil.pyladies.com/&quot;&gt;Pyladies Brasil&lt;/a&gt;, 
a group that encourages, trains and helps women to enter and grow on technology. 
The group &lt;a href=&quot;https://afropython.org/&quot;&gt;Afro Python&lt;/a&gt;, that works on increasing the representation 
of black people within the technology area, was also represented in the discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pandemic had a huge impact on local meetings and the members talked about their 
experience in managing the community, engaging people and dealing with 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zoom_fatigue&quot;&gt;zoom fatigue&lt;/a&gt;. 
The return of in-person activities also brought new demands like recording the talks,
sync and async activities and sanitary measures against COVID.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brazil is one of the most unequal countries in the world, part of the discussion was 
focused on how technology can provide social transformation for underrepresented groups. 
The whole Python Nordeste organization focused on diversity and inclusion by offering tickets 
to communities and non-governmental organizations, centered the attention on the LGBTQIA+ 
community and on how to provide a safe and welcoming environment for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;algorithmic-biases-and-how-to-combat-them&quot;&gt;Algorithmic biases and how to combat them&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Algorithms can discriminate. Racism and sexism are some of the bias that can exist in AI algorithms. 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/luiz-fernando-de-lima/&quot;&gt;Luiz Fernando&lt;/a&gt; presented his master’s research 
about how to build fair machine learning models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Algorithms can discriminate. How to combat them?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fairness algorithms try to remove or mitigate biases skewed towards a particular group of people. 
There are multiple methodologies to make algorithms more fair, from the most naive approaches like 
omitting variables from the model to most advanced approaches like fairness by design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luiz’s research was focused on fairness by design strategies that can be applied to change 
machine learning models in a way that guarantees the expected fairness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AI development is a very interdisciplinary field but few companies have interdisciplinary teams. 
Beyond technical strategies a diverse team helps to instigate social and ethical debates about how a model need to be adapted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-ai-can-impact-the-populations-health&quot;&gt;How AI can impact the population’s health?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fernanda Wanderley talked about how AI can be applied in healthcare solutions. She presented a computer vision
application that reads an x-ray and detects lung damage, increasing the priority in the emergency 
service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The AI isn’t developed to replace doctors but to assistant healthcare workers&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The application introduced by her was using doctors as annotators for medical images. The doctors were 
annotating the regions where they detect pleural effusion. The efforts of the annotators and the data science team 
enabled reducing the service time and increasing the agility to attend risk cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;using-ipyannotator-for-traffic-annotation&quot;&gt;Using Ipyannotator for traffic annotation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/palaimon/ipyannotator&quot;&gt;Ipyannotator&lt;/a&gt; is an annotation framework design which is customizable 
and runs in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://jupyter.org/&quot;&gt;Jupyter notebook environment&lt;/a&gt;. The tool allows users to create their own 
datasets, improve existing ones or explore the data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Machine learning applications combine code and data to generate results. For many years, the industry has 
focused on the code aspect and was using data as a static asset. Now, the industry is moving to a more 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://datacentricai.org/&quot;&gt;data-centric AI&lt;/a&gt;
approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ipyannotator is one of the tools that can be very helpful for data science teams to understand, create and improve 
their data. In this presentation I talked about the technologies used to develop Ipyannotator and how it was used in the 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bmvi.de/SharedDocs/DE/Artikel/DG/mfund-projekte/citycount.html&quot;&gt;CityCount project&lt;/a&gt;, which developed a cost-effective, mobile
AI-based counting device that provides data and insights for traffic planning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;width: 20%; float: left; margin-right: 1em&quot; alt=&quot;Python Nordeste logo. A 'Caju' (fruit) with a snake around&quot; src=&quot;/assets/pyne-logo.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;
Python Nordeste logo
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The return of in-person conferences in Brazil couldn’t be done in a better way than 
Python Nordeste did. It was an inclusive and well-rounded event. The organization really did a good job.
Any pythonista or person interested in technology would be happy to attend Python Nordeste.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">From August 26th to August 28th 2022 I attended the Python Nordeste, the biggest Python event in northeast of Brazil. It was the return of in-person conferences in the country. Focused on the communities, the event slogan was “People &amp;gt; Technology”.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Literate programming with Jupyter notebooks + nbdev + Quarto</title><link href="https://itepifanio.github.io/2022/08/16/literate-programming.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Literate programming with Jupyter notebooks + nbdev + Quarto" /><published>2022-08-16T20:09:20+00:00</published><updated>2022-08-16T20:09:20+00:00</updated><id>https://itepifanio.github.io/2022/08/16/literate-programming</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://itepifanio.github.io/2022/08/16/literate-programming.html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://jupyter.org/&quot;&gt;Jupyter notebook&lt;/a&gt; development environment is very popular in 
the scientific Python community. With this tool you can write markdown and code in the 
same file, which can increase the readability of the program. This paradigm is known as 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Literate_programming&quot;&gt;literate programming&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An example of a 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/palaimon/ipyannotator/blob/main/nbs/11_build_annotator_tutorial.ipynb&quot;&gt;Jupyter notebook including a section of markdown and Python code&lt;/a&gt; 
is shown in the following.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/jupyter-markdown-and-code.png&quot; alt=&quot;A small piece of a Jupyter notebook that inclues a block with markdown text and another with python code&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Literate programming is a very well regarded concept, formally discussed by
respected researchers like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Donald_Knuth&quot;&gt;Donald Knuth&lt;/a&gt;. 
At the same time, Jupyter notebooks are considered inefficient for serious software development.
This controversy led to the famous 
“&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7jiPeIFXb6U&amp;amp;t=20s&quot;&gt;I don’t like notebooks&lt;/a&gt;” talk, 
responded by the 
“&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9Q6sLbz37gk&quot;&gt;I like Jupyter notebooks&lt;/a&gt;” talk that 
generated &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fast.ai/2020/10/28/code-of-conduct/&quot;&gt;quite some drama&lt;/a&gt; within the 
community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/i-like-notebooks.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Thumbnail of the &amp;quot;I like notebooks&amp;quot; video. It shows Squidward Tentacles on a stage dodgin tomatoes&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jupyter notebooks have been limited to explore data, small scripts, and 
educational materials. The recent introduction of nbdev, a python library, expanded the capabilities 
of notebooks. Nbdev allows the development and distribution of python packages using the literate 
programming style, as well as test, document, and develop technical files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Nbdev allows you to tell a story with your code. It is a practical and powerful tool!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nbdev has proven to be uselful in developing big and serious projects, like 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/fastai/fastai&quot;&gt;FastAi&lt;/a&gt;.
Relying on nbdev and Jupyter notebook allows software development with quality and the 
benefits of the literate programming style.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;experience&quot;&gt;Experience&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first experience with nbdev was weird. Working with Jupyter notebooks for 
software development didn’t feel natural, as expected, afterall it’s 
a new paradigm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The software tool that I’m currently working on, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/palaimon/ipyannotator&quot;&gt;Ipyannotator&lt;/a&gt;, is an open source 
framework for annotations with a Graphical User Interface (GUI) that works on 
top of Jupyter notebook. Ipyannotator development was possible due to the nbdev 
allowing us to test the software on notebooks and export the code as a Python library.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;After 10 months of developing software with Jupyter notebook I feel that this has 
increased my productivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This software paradigm allowed me to keep my documentation up to date since the documentation is written right above my Python code block. This literate programming paradigm 
also reduces the mental lapse of going back to old code, making it easier to understand 
previous design decisions, since they are already documented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;quarto&quot;&gt;Quarto&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On July 28th, nbdev released its second version and incorporated another open source tool 
into its arsenal, &lt;a href=&quot;https://quarto.org/&quot;&gt;Quarto&lt;/a&gt;. Quarto allows the creation of technical 
content using Python, R or Julia, using files such as Jupyter notebooks, markdown, 
R Notebooks and allowing to export these files as articles, websites, blogs, HTML, PDFs, 
EPub, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Quarto is a complete solution to easily write any technical material with the tools you already know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This tool is so awesome that I’m planning to migrate my personal blog from Jekyll to Quarto. 
It’s clean in design, usability, and ability to execute code embedded by text blocks, which fits perfectly any technical 
writing requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nbdev noticed how powerful Quarto can be.
This addition helps with website development and documentation rendering. 
The first version of nbdev already contained some of these features, however, 
they were rudimentary and required several workarounds. In the second version nbdev added Quarto to its core.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Development with nbdev and Quarto can increase the productivity of many teams, helping to document and 
tell the story of your software. These tools also expand the possibilities of software development, as 
was the case with the already exemplified &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/palaimon/ipyannotator&quot;&gt;Ipyannotator&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like any tool, it also has its tradeoffs. One of them is the lack of auto-complete in Jupyter notebooks, 
something that can be avoided by using the visual code extension. Another problem is that Jupyter notebook 
writes json files, a format that makes git conflict resolution difficult due to extra metadata alongside the code. 
Making conflict resolution difficult minimizes the chances of big teams working on the same software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, the addition of Quarto shows that nbdev already plans to use other files besides Jupyter notebooks 
in its development core. This enables large teams to develop software with literate programming, 
decreasing the main tradeoff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in trying nbdev you can check the following reference: 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fast.ai/2022/07/28/nbdev-v2/&quot;&gt;nbdev+Quarto: A new secret weapon for productivity&lt;/a&gt;.
If you’re curious about Jupyter notebooks code for software development just check 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/palaimon/ipyannotator/tree/main/nbs&quot;&gt;Ipyannotator code&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The Jupyter notebook development environment is very popular in the scientific Python community. With this tool you can write markdown and code in the same file, which can increase the readability of the program. This paradigm is known as literate programming.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lazy horizontal scroll</title><link href="https://itepifanio.github.io/2021/10/23/lazy-horizontal-scroll.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lazy horizontal scroll" /><published>2021-10-23T20:09:20+00:00</published><updated>2021-10-23T20:09:20+00:00</updated><id>https://itepifanio.github.io/2021/10/23/lazy-horizontal-scroll</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://itepifanio.github.io/2021/10/23/lazy-horizontal-scroll.html">&lt;p&gt;Recently I came across with the following scenario: a management software of workflows that allow the user to dynamic create its kanbans (like the one in the image below). One of the users set its kanban to have 38 columns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The software was design in a way that every kanban column made a request to the backend, in this scenario 38 new requests were made every time a user access the kanban page. This not only overload the server but also the database.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dev-to-uploads.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/articles/6ui3slceaoxqovpxm1uo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Kanban image with five columns. The columsn in the sequence: stories, todo, in progress, testing, done&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First we needed to decrease the number of requests, limiting the requests to the columns that were visible to the user. After that we had to make sure that if the user scrolls to the end of the page at once, the columns would not request the data unless they were visible for a certain amount of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;limiting-loading-to-visible-cards&quot;&gt;Limiting loading to visible cards&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Javascript offers an API called &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/IntersectionObserver&quot;&gt;IntersectionObserver&lt;/a&gt; that allow us to watch HTML elements and check its visibility on screen. The code below shows its most basic operation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-javascript highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;onIntersection&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;elements&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;elements&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;forEach&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;element&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;element&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;isIntersecting&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
          &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;console&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;log&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;element&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;is visible&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;});&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;};&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;observer&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;IntersectionObserver&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;onIntersection&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;observer&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;observe&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;document&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;querySelector&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;.my-elements&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;));&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The function &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;onIntersection&lt;/code&gt; is responsable for the logic that will be applied to the visible elements, it takes a list of elements and checks that if they’re visible  (&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt; element.isIntersecting &lt;/code&gt;) then something will be done, in which case a console message is displayed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ` IntersectionObserver ` API call is made and set to the ` observer ` variable. The ` observer ` object will then be able to observe elements in the HTML and execute logic only when they are visible on the user’s screen. In my case, for the giant kanban, this was enough to limit the 38 requests as the page loaded to just 5, but if the user scrolled the page to its end at once several requests would be made (the other 33 requests).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;load-only-after-a-certain-time-of-the-visible-element-on-the-page&quot;&gt;Load only after a certain time of the visible element on the page&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ` IntersectionObserver ` API has a &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.dev/intersectionobserver-v2/&quot;&gt;version 2&lt;/a&gt; that allows capturing how long a certain HTML element was visible on the screen and this would easily solve the element loading problem HTML only after a certain amount of time. However, version 2 still doesn’t have its implementations compatible with most browsers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my specific case I was using a parent component that rendered the 38 child elements and I couldn’t check when those 38 child elements were finished rendering to observe them with the ` InsertersectionObserver `, so control how long each element was visible in the screen got a little more complicated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each of the 38 child elements knew when they were rendering themselves, so you could use the ` IntersectionObserver ` internally on each of them. Using the ` setTimeout ` function of the javascript you can observe the element after a certain time specified in milliseconds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have 38 elements, but most are not visible on the screen and become visible when scrolling, with the ` setTimeout ` delay this action still takes some time to be executed. During scrolling, when the element visible on the screen has not yet triggered the specified &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;setTimeout&lt;/code&gt; and the user has already scrolled to the next element, it is possible to remove the timeout of the previous element from the stack and then load only the next element. The following code shows this strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-javascript highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;border border-black m-1 p-10 min-w-max h-10&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
       &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;&quot;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
       &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;init&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;() =&amp;gt; {
           let timeout;
           let loadColumn = function (elements) {
               clearTimeout(timeout);
               
               timeout = setTimeout(function() {
                   elements.forEach(element =&amp;gt; {
                       if (element.isIntersecting) {
                           // do something
                           observer.unobserve(element.target);
                       }
                   });
               }, 750);
           }
           
           let observer = new IntersectionObserver(loadColumn);
           let target = $el;
           observer.observe(target);
       }&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sr&quot;&gt;/div&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the component is loaded into the page it already starts looking at itself using the ` loadColumn ` function. Such function removes the previous timeouts (which were not triggered) from the execution stack and adds a new timeout which after 750 milliseconds does something and removes the observation to not redo the same logic if the element becomes visible again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my case the logic was the request to the server so I only needed to load the data once and then ignore it if the element was visible again on the page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Did you find the above code syntax strange? This javascript microframework is called &lt;a href=&quot;https://alpinejs.dev/&quot;&gt;AlpineJS&lt;/a&gt; and that’s what I used to develop the complete solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A simpler POC, without the request to the server, can be seen below. After being visible on your screen the white squares will turn black indicating the request to the server.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p data-height=&quot;400&quot; data-theme-id=&quot;0&quot; data-slug-hash=&quot;PoKqGPm&quot; data-default-tab=&quot;result&quot; data-user=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;codepen&quot;&gt;See the Pen &lt;a href=&quot;http://codepen.io//pen/PoKqGPm/&quot;&gt;Carregamento lento com scroll horizontal&lt;/a&gt; by  (&lt;a href=&quot;http://codepen.io/&quot;&gt;@&lt;/a&gt;) on &lt;a href=&quot;http://codepen.io&quot;&gt;CodePen&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//assets.codepen.io/assets/embed/ei.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in seeing a solution with vanilla javascript &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.codeguage.com/tutorials/lazy-loading/intersection-observer&quot;&gt;this was my reference&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Recently I came across with the following scenario: a management software of workflows that allow the user to dynamic create its kanbans (like the one in the image below). One of the users set its kanban to have 38 columns.</summary></entry></feed>